<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's interest: or, Means to promote the consumption of English wooll to populate the nation and raise the value of lands, and the product of them, by increasing the manufacturers of cloth and stuffs made of English wooll, and silk, and mohair-yarn in this kingdom. Published to prevent misunderstandings, and that right judgment may be given in a matter of so great concern to the nation. Contained in reasons intended to be offered to a Committee of the Honourable House of Commons, who appointed to hear the weavers, against a Bill prohibiting the wear of silks and stuffs for six months of the year. (July the 9th, 1689.) By William James. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
            <author>James, William, fl. 1689-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216312</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46636)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1911:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's interest: or, Means to promote the consumption of English wooll to populate the nation and raise the value of lands, and the product of them, by increasing the manufacturers of cloth and stuffs made of English wooll, and silk, and mohair-yarn in this kingdom. Published to prevent misunderstandings, and that right judgment may be given in a matter of so great concern to the nation. Contained in reasons intended to be offered to a Committee of the Honourable House of Commons, who appointed to hear the weavers, against a Bill prohibiting the wear of silks and stuffs for six months of the year. (July the 9th, 1689.) By William James. Licensed and entred according to order.</title>
                  <author>James, William, fl. 1689-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author, and are to be sold at his house in Katharine-wheel-Alley without Bishops-gate, next to the steps, within the Brick-Wall, as you go out of Hand-alley, or New Street, into Petticoat-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32472:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>England's Intereſt:</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Or, Means to promote the Conſumption of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, to Populate the Nation and raiſe the Value of Lands, and the Product of them, by increaſing the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facturers of Cloth and Stuffs made of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, and Silk, and Mohair-Yarn in this Kingdom. Publiſhed to prevent Miſunderſtandings, and that right Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be given in a matter of ſo great concern to the Nation. Contained in Reaſons intended to be offered to a Committee of the Honourable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who appointed to hear the Weavers, againſt a Bill prohibiting the wear of Silks and Stuffs for ſix Months of the Year. (<hi>July</hi> the 9th, 1689.)</p>
            </argument>
            <byline>By WILLIAM JAMES.</byline>
            <p>Licenſed and Entred according to Order.</p>
            <p>I Shall <hi>firſt</hi> ſhew, that this Bill will not anſwer the Deſign of it, which is a greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Wooll, but greatly leſſen it. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall take notice of the undeniable evil Effects, and conſequences of it. And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Humbly offer to conſideration, what are the Obſtructions to the Conſumption of Wooll, and a proper means to promote it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>That this will not anſwer the Deſign of the Bill, appears thus.</head>
               <p>It is ackowledged by all intelligent Perſons, that the greateſt Conſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, is to <hi>Turky;</hi> our Merchants tranſporting thither 25 or 30000 Cloaths yearly, which are Manufactured here, and made of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll; the making of which Cloaths, employs many Thouſand People, and is more than this Nation and the whole World beſides conſumes; for there is little Tranſported to other parts of the World, and not one tenth part worn of it in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> that little which is worn in <hi>England,</hi> is moſt home-made Cloth put out by poor labouring Men in the Country, for their own uſe and wear; and the generality of the Cloaths worn here by the Nobility and Gentry, and Tradeſmen of the beſt Rank and Quality, have little, if any, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll in them; and thoſe worn by ordinary Tradeſmen, not above one third.</p>
               <p>Now, the chief Return for thoſe Cloaths, are Silk, and Mohair-Yarn; <hi>Turky</hi> not affording any other Commodities fit for <hi>England,</hi> to the value of one eighth part of our Cloath tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither; therefore by this Reſtraint of wearing Silks, this Trade to <hi>Turky</hi> muſt needs be Reduced, and in time be brought to little or nothing. For if the Conſumption of Silk and Hair be leſſened in <hi>England,</hi> the Conſumption of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloath will be proportionably leſſen'd in <hi>Turky;</hi> and conſequenly, leſſen the Conſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll. For it cannot be thought, that thoſe Perſons, who now wear Silk and Hair Stuffs (when prohibited to be worn) will wear coarſe Cloaths, made of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll; and as for others, they wear them already. So that there will be no Addition to the Conſumption of Wooll here in <hi>England</hi> by virtue of this Act.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the prohibiting the wear of Silk and Hair Stuffs in the Winter Seaſon, doth in a meaſure, and will in time utterly exclude the Manufacturing of Silks and Stuffs in <hi>England,</hi> (which Employs Scores, if not Hundreds of Thouſands), for that moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Silks being thick and ſubſtantial, are fitteſt for the Winter-ſeaſon, and not only their Silks, but Stuffs, as <hi>Shaggs, Prunels, Barratines, Tamalets, Mohairs, Farendines,</hi> and others, which conſume the greateſt part of our <hi>Turky</hi> Silk, and Mohair-Yarn, are worn chiefly by Women in that time, and part of the Year; whereas the thinner and ſlighter Silks, that are wore in the Summer, are brought in fully Manufactured from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and other parts, there being not one fifth part of the Silks then worn of our own Manufacture.</p>
               <p>Again, this Act prohibits the wear of Stuffs mixt with Silk: now, there are ſeveral ſorts of Stuffs, as <hi>Bombazines, Antharines, Seyes, Tamines, Eſtimines, Druggets, Drafts,</hi> and many other <hi>Norwich-Stuffs,</hi> which are made of <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Wooll, and not above one tenth part of Silk in them; and becauſe of that little Silk in them, cannot be worn, which will hinder the Conſumption of Wooll ten times more than all the Cloath worn by virtue of this Act, will promote it. So that it is manifeſt, this Act inſtead of promoting the Conſumption of Wooll, will greatly leſſen it, and in little time bring that Staple-Commodity and Trade to Ruin.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only add to the foregoing Reaſons, the Conſideration of the <hi>French</hi> Nation, who by reaſon of the Tranſportation of our Wooll (by evil-minded and intereſſed Men, Enemies to the Nation, and Contemners of the Laws) are become Competitors with us in this Trade to <hi>Turky,</hi> and do grow, and greatly increaſe in it; ſo that they now ſell as great Quantities as we, and are ſtriving daily to outvy us in that profitable Trade. And this Act will certainly give them the greateſt Advantage imaginable, to perfect this their Deſign, and in time to root us quite out of it, to the inconceivable loſs of this Nation. So that from this Argument alſo, it appears as clear as the Light at Noonday, That this Act will leſſen the Vent of our Cloath made of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32472:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Turky.</hi> Therefore we do hope, for this, and the foregoing Reaſons, the Parliament will lay aſide this Act, or find ſome other way for the Vending and Conſumption of our Wooll, (and ſuch as may keep at Work, and Employ ſo many thouſand People, as the Woollen and Silk Manufactures do) either here in <hi>England,</hi> or ſome other Parts of the World, before they paſs this Act, which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> put ſo great a ſtop to the Conſumption of it in <hi>Turky.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The evil Conſequences of this Act follow.</head>
               <p>By this Act, the chiefeſt and moſt beneficial Manufactures of <hi>England,</hi> will be diſcouraged and ruined; for they employ more People than all the Trades in <hi>England</hi> beſides. As to the Silk-Trade, it Employs both Old and Young, Blind and Lame, who are able to get ſomething of a Livelihood by it; who otherwiſe muſt neceſſarily beg their Bread, and be chargeable to the Places of their Abodes; and upon the moſt modeſt Computation, there are Employed and Maintained by this Trade in and about the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> above One hundred thouſand Perſons, beſides great Numbers at <hi>Canterbury, Norwitch,</hi> and other Places. If this Act paſs into a Law, theſe muſt and will immediately be turned out of Employment, and be forced either to Beg, real, or Starve, or do worſe; and as for the Cloathing-Trade, they will ſoon feel the effects of it, for they are dependant one upon another, as may be gathered from the preceding Reaſons; which demonſtrate that the more of our own Manufactured Silks are worn in <hi>England,</hi> the more Cloath made of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll is vended; and this Act, leſſening the Conſumption of Silk, muſt conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently leſſen the Conſumption of their Cloath, and take off the Employment of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of that Trade. So that this Act will not only deprive theſe great Numbers of People of their preſent and future Subſiſtence, and render them miſerable, who are now uſeful and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to the Nation; but alſo hinder other Foreign Proteſtants from coming here to reſide; a great number whereof have been, and now are, and many thouſands more may be, employed in this Silk and Hair Trade, were it duly encouraged.</p>
               <p>As to that Suppoſition, That the Silk and Hair Trade will be ſufficiently provided for, by the ſix Months time, wherein they are allowed to be worn; it will prove a great miſtake. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what hath been already ſaid, That the chiefeſt Conſumption of our Silk and Hair Stuffs, is in the Winter-ſeaſon; this alſo may be added, That this ſuppoſed ſix Months, will not employ the Silk Trade above three Months. For very few Perſons, if any, except the Nobility, do make Garments more than once in a quarter of a year: So that from <hi>July</hi> the 15th, to <hi>April</hi> the 15th, which is nine Months in the Year, the Mercers and Weavers muſt lie ſtill, and be idle. And as to the Hair Trade, which is conſiderable, and employs many Thouſands, that will be wholly loſt; the Commodities generally made of them, being worn only in the Winter-ſeaſon, except ſome few Perſons, who are employed in making of Camlets, which at this time doth not conſume one tenth Part of the Mohair-yarn that comes over for the Exchange of our Cloath. So that if Foreign Silks were prohibited, the Trade of Silk-weaving could not in that ſhort time make ſo many Silks as will anſwer the preſent Conſumption of Cloath to <hi>Turky:</hi> So that the Cloathing-Trade muſt neceſſarily decline, and the Manufacturers thereof, be expoſed to miſery for want of Employment, and the Conſumption of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll greatly diminiſhed.</p>
               <p>And the evil Influences of this Act will not ſtop here; but its ill Effects will extend to the Nobility and Gentry themſelves, to their inconceivable, if not irrecoverable loſs. For tho God hath bleſſed them with conſiderable Eſtates in Land; yet, if their Lands be unoccupied, they will be little the better for them; and that their Lands will lye unoccupied, at leaſt, the greateſt part of them, if this Act paſs into a Law, is moſt certain, becauſe of that great Poverty and Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation that ſo neceſſarily and demonſtraively will enſue upon it. It is manifeſt by Experience, that where a Manufacture, and much People are ſetled in any part of the Nation, there the Lands are not only occupied, but yield the greateſt Rents, and the Fruits thereof the greateſt Price. This Act will not only hinder the increaſe of People in thoſe Parts of the Nation that want them, but deprive thoſe parts of the Nation that have them, of their preſent and future Benefit by them; and in time may produce a general decay of Manufactures in the Nation. I would ſuppoſe, that by virtue of this Act, the price of Wooll ſhould be advanced to 12 <hi>p.</hi> a Pound, which is impoſſible; for the contrary, even the leſſening of the Price, will be the effects of it. But for Argument-ſake ſuppoſe it; then I will ask, Whether the advance of Wooll to 12 <hi>d.</hi> a Pound, will anſwer to the fall of their Corn 2 <hi>s.</hi> in a Buſhel, and their Beef, Mutton, Butter, and Cheeſe, 1 <hi>d.</hi> or 2 <hi>d.</hi> a Pound? And whether they had not better ſell their Wooll for a penny a Pound, nay, give it away, rather than have their other Fruits of their Land to fall ſo conſiderably by it? The ſolution of this Queſtion is nigh at hand, to the meaneſt Capacity. Now, that the fall and leſſening of the Price of theſe, will be the effects of this Act, is manifeſt; for when the People that ſhould eat them, ſome are ſo Poor they cannot buy them, and others Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport themſelves to other parts for a Livelihood; what will they do with them, except it be ſuppoſed they will turn Merchants, and Tranſport them after them; which if they do, I am ſure, Loſs muſt be the greateſt Debtor to Ballance the Accompt; which is a bad Pay-maſter.</p>
               <p>Again, if the Silk-Trade, now under ſo great diſcouragement by Foreign Importation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be capable of employing ſo many thouſand People, when it is rightly ſuppoſed that not one fourth part of the Silks conſumed in <hi>England,</hi> are Manufactured here, but in Foreign Parts; Will it not be an unſpeakable Prejudice to this Nation, if a ſtop be put to the growth of ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32472:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a Trade, that if encouraged, may and will Employ three or four hundred thouſand People more; by which (<hi>Proteſtant Trade,</hi> for ſo it may rightly be called) the Proteſtant Intereſt is, and may be encouraged and ſtrengthned, by employing thoſe Perſons of that Profeſſion, which are and may come over, to the Enriching the Nation, and raiſing the Price of Lands, and the Product of them. Yet this Act will not only ſtop the growth, but utterly deſtroy this ſo uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and beneficial a Manufacture; and is this a ſmall matter? nay, is it not a matter of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concern to the Nation? I do not queſtion, but upon conſideration of theſe things, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will lay aſide this Act, or at leaſtwiſe, before they Paſs it, find out ſome other Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thoſe vaſt multitudes of our Natives and Foreigners already here, and that ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon the Account of Religion, come hither; This is but reaſonable, and yet I am ſure im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
               <p>Therefore certainly this Act, of all others that ever men were miſtaken in, is moſt prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to the whole Kingdom; for if that be a true maxim (as doubtleſs it is,) That the ſafety of the King, Queen, and Kingdom, ſtands in the Multitude and Riches of the people; then this Act, which ſo inevitably tends to the depopulating and empoveriſhing the Nation, muſt render it indefenſible and miſerable; and it is ſo much the more aggravating, in that it will ruin and deſtroy that Trade, which is the moſt hopeful and ready means to render this Nation the moſt Flouriſhing, Rich, and Powerful Kingdom, and the Fortreſs of the Proteſtant Intereſt, and a ſure Refuge, under God, to all its Profeſſors. I am bold to ſay, That if all the Enemies in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom</hi> ſhould conſult together, they could not have deviſed a more proper and effectual means to overthrow the foundation of the Peace and Glory of this Nation, and the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Intereſt, than by this or ſuch like Acts, which will not only hinder the Increaſe of the People and Trade of this Nation, and conſequently the Strength and Riches of it; but alſo tends to the ruin of Trade, depopulating and empoveriſhing of it, and thereby renders it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defenſible, and unable to oppoſe their wicked deſigns againſt it.</p>
               <p>Far be it from me to think, that any Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, ſhould be influenced by any ſuch Counſels or Perſons; or that they would wittingly do the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, much leſs a thing ſo greatly prejudicial to the Intereſt of the Nation, and the Proteſtant Religion. Yet the effects of this Act, if it paſs, will be ſuch; and this, that Politick Prince the <hi>French</hi> King, well knows, who hath made himſelf and Nation powerful, by encouraging this Silk Trade, which employs ſo many Thouſands of his People, by Weaving them at home, and Tranſporting them abroad, both to Us and many other parts of the World. And it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, he hath endeavoured all along to ſuppreſs the growth of this Manufacture here, by holding Treaties of Trade, with Promiſes to come to an Equality; but hath ſo managed it, by ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile means, and powerful inſtruments, that inſtead of abating the diſproportion of Trade, even in the time of Treaty, it hath increaſed to a prodigious Exceſs, even to above a Million in one year, as can be made appear by the Cuſtom-Houſe Books; beſide Prohibited Goods not Entred, which amounts to ſome Hundreds of Thouſands more. The very Silks and Linnen Cloth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from <hi>France</hi> in one Year, amounts to above Six hundred thouſand pounds more than all the Growth and Manufactures of <hi>England</hi> exported thither; which prodigious Sum muſt be paid in Money, to the exhauſting our Coin. So that it is no wonder that he is grown ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and gives Laws, as it were, and bids defiance to the whole World; and that he endeavours by all means to ſuppreſs the growth of this Trade here, when he gains even from hence ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Hundred thouſand Pounds a year by it, to the enriching him and his people, and impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing us. And there can nothing doubtleſs be more conducing to his Deſigns (and will be matter of rejoicing to him and his Jeſuitical Crew) than a Reſtraint of Weaving our own Silks, by a Law; for that it will put an opportunity into his hand to obtain the whole Trade to <hi>Turky,</hi> which is the moſt profitable to this Nation; for that it encourages Navigation, and takes off ſo great a quantity of our Cloth, which employs ſo many Thouſands of our People; and by this means, this Nation, which is at preſent ſo great a check to his ambitious Deſigns, will ſoon come under his Power, ſo as to give us what Laws he pleaſes; which God in Mercy prevent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Obſtructions to the Conſumption of Wooll, and Means to Promote it, follow.</head>
               <p>The great Obſtruction to the Conſumption of Wooll, hath been our wearing great quantities of Silks and other Commodities from Foreign parts; eſpecially from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>India;</hi> as Silks called <hi>Perſians;</hi> and <hi>Callicoes</hi> imported by the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company: Beſides the Silks, the <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coes</hi> laſt mentioned, contribute more to the leſſening the Conſumption of Wool, than moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are aware of, and is little regarded. A conſiderable part and number of this Nation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Children from 1 or 2, to 12 or 13 years old; and the generality of theſe do wear Frocks, and ſome Petticoats of ſtained and ſtriped <hi>Callicoes;</hi> and of late, many others do wear them for Petticoats, which hath greatly hindred the Conſumption of many pretty Stuffs, ſome made all of Wooll, and ſome with a little Silk mixt with Wooll, which were formerly uſed in ſuch Veſtments; and which if again uſed, would conſume more <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, than can well be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined; I am ſure to ten times the Quantity that would be worn the more in Cloth, if this Act ſhould paſs.</p>
               <p>By that which hath been already ſaid, the means of Promoting the Conſumption of Wool, is near at hand, and viſible to all, if there be an Act paſs ſo ſtrict, that if poſſible, it may wholly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32472:3"/>
the Importation of ſuch Silks, which the Parliament in their Great Wiſdoms ſhall think meet to prohibit; and to countenance and encourage the uſe and wear of our own Manufactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Silks and Stuffs, which are the product of our own Woollen Manufactures; this would greatly increaſe the Conſumption of Wooll: And the former Reaſons and Arguments do ſufficiently demonſtrate to any impartial conſidering man, That the more Silk and Hair Stuffs manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured here in <hi>England,</hi> are worn and conſumed, the greater will be the Conſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll: And beſides theſe undeniable Reaſons, we appeal to the Clothiers themſelves, who manufacture thoſe Cloaths made of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, who doubtleſs are the moſt competent Judges in this caſe; and who are ready to aſſert the truth thereof, when called to it; and it is an undoubted truth, That he that wears a Silk or Mohair Garment of our own manufacturing, doth conſume more <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll, than numbers of perſons that wear Cloth; therefore if the Conſumption of Wooll be a common Good to this Nation, as doubtleſs it is, they are the beſt Common-wealths-men, that wear Silks and Stuffs of our own Manufacturing.</p>
               <p>Let it not be thought, that I hyperbolize, or over-ſpeak and magnifie the uſefulneſs and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficialneſs of this Silk Manufacture in <hi>England,</hi> out of Intereſt, or any other but good deſign; for what hath been ſaid of it, hath not only been demonſtrated by undeniable and convincing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but is made good by Experience; for ſince that good Act, Prohibiting <hi>French</hi> Silks for three years, there hath been a far greater quantity of Silks made in <hi>England,</hi> than ever was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time; and the Price of Wooll ſince that time, hath been much advanced; and now ſince there hath been an interruption of Trade to <hi>Turky,</hi> by reaſon of the War and Diſtractions there, the Price of Wooll is greatly leſſened; which is a clear demonſtration, That it is the want of Exportation thither, that is the cauſe of it, and not the wearing of our own Silks here. And as for for Fine Cloth, the conſumption of which ſort only, will be promoted by this Act, it hath been more generally worn in ſome years laſt paſt, by the Nobility, Gentry, and Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of beſt Quality, than in former years, and yet the Conſumption of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wooll hath been little or nothing promoted by it; indeed it hath much promoted the Conſumption of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Wooll, which we do not grudg, but let it have its courſe, foraſmuch as it employs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people; but we hope the Parliament will not promote it by ſuch a Law, that is to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of a Trade ten times more valuable and uſeful in all reſpects, as the weaving of Silks and Stuffs of our own manufacturing, hath been ſo plainly demonſtrated to be.</p>
               <p>An effectual Prohibition of all Foreign Silks that ſhall be thought prejudicial, and hinder the Conſumption of our own Manufactured Silks and Stuffs, without any injunction to wear Cloth or Stuffs made of all Wooll, will be a ſufficient Encouragement to, and greatly advance the Price of Wooll in a little ſeaſon, and alſo populate the Nation; to the increaſe of the price of Lands, and the Fruits and Product of it: And if to this, the Parliament ſhall ſee cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit the wearing of Painted Callicoes in Frocks, Petticoats, and other outward Garments, and lay no reſtraint upon any one, but give equal Countenance and Encouragement to all the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of Silks, Stuffs, and Cloth, this would not only advance the Price of Wooll, by reaſon of the great uſe of it, but in few years it will ſet ſome Hundred thouſands of Perſons at work, more than now is; it would alſo prevent the Exportation of our Wooll, and the Deſigns of thoſe who are now Competitors with us in that profitable Trade to <hi>Turky;</hi> for there will be ſo much uſe of it by our Clothiers, and Stuff Weavers, that no perſon will have ſo much as a temptation to tranſport it, for want of a Price for it; and ſo that ſtaple Commodity will be kept within our own Nation, to the great increaſe of it in Riches, Strength, and Power.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch therefore, as this Trade is ſo uſeful and beneficial to the King, Queen and whole Kingdom, to the Proteſtant Intereſt, and every particular perſon in the Nation, we hope the Parliament will make a Fence about it, and ſecure it from all violation, that it may be as ſacred as <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf, and a brand of Infamy put upon thoſe that ſhall endeavour to make the leaſt breach upon it, and thereby prevent the Deſigns of all the Enemies to our Religion and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore we Pray, That they would not only lay aſide this Act, which diſcourageth; but paſs ſuch an Act, as in their Wiſdoms they ſhall think moſt meet, to encourage this moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and beneficial Trade of the Nation, which for many years laſt paſt, hath been diſcouraged by Foreign Importations, unuſual long Mournings, and other ſubtleties of the Enemies of this Nation, to the Ruin of many of the Manufacturers thereof. And this is no other than what we Hope for, do Expect, and yet have confidence we ſhall Obtain from our Proteſtant King, Queen and Parliament: <hi>Whom God long Preſerve.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold at his Houſe in <hi>Katharine-wheel-Alley</hi> without <hi>Biſhops-gate,</hi> next to the Steps, within the <hi>Brick-Wall,</hi> as you go out of <hi>Hand-alley,</hi> or <hi>New-Street,</hi> into <hi>Petticoat-lane.</hi> 1689.</p>
            <div type="advert">
               <p>WHO alſo hath been well known for many years, to <hi>Trim</hi> all manner of <hi>Silks,</hi> as well <hi>Colours,</hi> as <hi>Blacks</hi> and <hi>Venetians,</hi> after the beſt manner; and to Take off the <hi>Tarniſh,</hi> as well as to <hi>Trim</hi> and <hi>Beautifie</hi> all manner of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver</hi> Stuffs, and Stuffs mixt with <hi>Wooll, Hair,</hi> and <hi>Silk,</hi> as <hi>Coſſairs, Barratines; Antharines,</hi> &amp;c. who will take care to do them as Well and as Cheap (according to the nature of the Works) for thoſe <hi>Mercers, Weavers,</hi> or <hi>Others,</hi> that ſhall Employ him therein, as any Perſon whatſoever.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:32472:3"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
